<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lord George Digbies apologie for himselfe published the fourth of January, Anno Dom. 1642.</title>
            <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4762A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171658</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77518)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171658)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2584:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lord George Digbies apologie for himselfe published the fourth of January, Anno Dom. 1642.</title>
                  <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages are badly stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bristol, George Digby, --  Earl of, 1612-1677.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Lord <hi>George Digbies</hi> Apologie for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, publiſhed the fourth of <hi>Ianuary, Anno Dom.</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>IT may be wondred at, that after well nigh a years groaning under the moſt inſupportable burthen of publick diſpleaſure, and cenſure, I ſhould now conſider my ſelfe ſo much, as, in a generall calamity, to make an Apologie to the world; or ſhould hope, that at a time when ſo great clouds of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and diſ-eſteeme hang over perſons of the moſt cleare, and unblemiſhed reputations, any thing I can ſay may reconcile me to thoſe affections, which have been tranſported with ſo much violence to my prejudice. But whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever knoweth me well, and the great trouble of minde I endured when I found my ſelfe (by what demerit, God is my judge, I cannot gueſſe) fallen from that proportion of eſteem with my Countrey (of which I was prouder than I can be of any worldly preferment) into ſo eminent a degree of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour with the repreſentative body thereof (upon whoſe wiſdome and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority no man hath looked with more reverence, and veneration) that I was marked out as an enemy to the Common-wealth, I am ſure cannot but expect from me ſome diſcovery of that ſence, and that I ſhould, at leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to diſtinguiſh my misfortunes from my faults, whereby ſuch, who are not engaged in a peremptory uncharitableneſſe, may find cauſe to change the opinion they have taken upon truſt of mee.</p>
            <p>Nor am I out of hope, that the experience men have ſince had of the times inclination to calumnie, by the declining of ſo many perſons of honor, and integrity in the popular eſtimation, may at the laſt, open away to ſo much juſtice and ingenuity on my behalfe, that all men may diſcerne in their owne right, that if they ſhall ſo credulouſly conſent, upon generall diſcourſes, to ſacrifice a third mans honor, and reputation, they ſhall open a doore to let in ruine to themſelves, and may quickly loſe the advantage of their owne innocence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall begin my unfortunate ſtory from the begining of this Parliament, reflecting no farther back upon the precedent, than in a remembrance of the great comfort <hi>I</hi> then received in my Countries acceptation of my firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in its ſervice, at a time, as ſome were pleaſed to expreſſe it, when the Court was at the higheſt, whether to work upon mens ambitions, or fears. Before that time <hi>I</hi> am ſure <hi>I</hi> was as unacquainted with Action, as with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, having kept more company with books, than with men: and being ſo well content with that ſociety, that <hi>I</hi> had as little ambition, as merit to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my condition. To this Parliament <hi>I</hi> was ſent on the behalfe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Countrey wherein <hi>I</hi> lived: and truely, if <hi>I</hi> brought any paſſion or affection thither with me, it was my former warmth improved againſt thoſe preſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, and the perſons who begot thoſe preſſures, which were grievous to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and againſt theſe, <hi>I</hi> will without vanity ſay, that <hi>I</hi> brought as great a reſolution to diſcharge my conſcience, and my duty, as any man in that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and had the happineſſe for ſome moneths, to receive that teſtimony.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171658:4"/>
            <p>My converſation was, and I made or endeavoured to make my friendſhips, with thoſe, whoſe experience, and abilities, were moſt eminent for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſervice, and to the reputation, and authority of theſe men, I confeſſe for a while, <hi>I</hi> gave my ſelfe up with as much ſubmiſſion as a man could, without reſigning the uſe of his own underſtanding in any thing that was neceſſary, or but probably pretended to be neceſſary for the Common-wealth, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver differed in the leaſt degree, but in improvements, in reall alterations, which were to be govern'd by prudentiall motives, we were not alwayes of one minde. And whoſoever remembereth the paſſages of that time, muſt call to mind, that the firſt declination <hi>I</hi> ſuffered from the intereſt I ſeem'd to have, was in the buſineſſe of the Church: in which, having had frequent conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with the chiefeſt agents for a Reformation, and finding no three men to agree upon what they would have in the place of that they all reſolved to remove, I agreed not with the prevailing ſenſe, having not hardineſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to incline to a mutation, which would evidently have ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the peace, proſperity, and intereſt of the whole Kingdom. And thus from the firſt debate of Epiſcopacy, upon the <hi>London</hi> Petition, all men obſerv'd the date of my unmerited favour began to expire, Then came on the tryall of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> in the which I muſt ſay, I failed not of my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in proving the charge and evidence, before thoſe who were to judge of both. In the diſcharging of that duty, it was my fortune, by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky acception of ſome expreſſions of mine, to draw upon me a ſharp malignity from ſome perſons of much intereſt in the Houſe, which never failed to manifeſt it ſelfe after that accident, upon every the leaſt occaſion.</p>
            <p>About this time I was told by a friend, that I loſt much of my credit by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerv'd to be ſo much at Court; I replyed, that I had not then the ſame juſtice with other men, who were there more then I, though they avowed it leſſe, that it was a principall joy to me, to ſee thoſe perſons who had been the prime Actors in the happy Reformation of this Parliament, ſo acceptable at Court, and likely to have ſo great a ſhare in the chief places there, and the conduct of affairs for the future. That ſince it had pleaſed His Majeſty to give ſo plenary a Redreſſe to all the grievances of His Subjects, and to ſecure them for ever from the like invaſions, by ſuch a wall of braſſe as the Trieniall Bill, I conceive that thence forward, there was no more to be thought on; but how in a gratefull return to His Majeſty, to advance his Honour, and Plenty, according as before ſuch happy ſettlements, had often heard thoſe principall intendents of the publike good moſt ſolemnly profeſſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that the Court and Country were in truth, now to be all of a piece, and there would hereafter be no more cauſe of jealouſie between them: Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, that, howſoever I thought my ſelfe as likely to do good there, as to receive hurt.</p>
            <p>The firſt evidence I had of the disfavour of the Houſe of Commons (where I had ſerved with all faithfullneſſe, diligence, and humility,) was upon the printing of my Speech to the Bill of Attainder of the Earl of <hi>Strafford.</hi> As for the Good-Fridayes exerciſe which the delivery of it in the Houſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd
<pb facs="tcp:171658:4"/> me, I reputed that a moſt comfortable and eminent teſtimony of the continuance ſtill of much juſtice and favour towards mee in that Honorable Houſe; ſince, after a dozen diſtinct charges upon the ſeverall paſſages of that Speech, urged againſt me with great ſtrictneſſe and acrimony, by that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the moſt eminent perſons there, both in abilities and intereſts, and at a time when certainly moſt men of my opinion were at their devotions, they were not able after four houres debate to expoſe me, either upon the mayn matter, or upon the bye, unto the leaſt apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>For the thing it ſelf, <hi>I</hi> will ſay no more of it, but that it hapned to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a very unpopular argument; but the cauſe and circumſtance of the printing it, was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> did not find only that it was unfaithfully reported, and uncharitably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, but was informed, that Copies went abroad of it ſo falſly and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly collected, as made the whole Speech a juſtification of my Lord of <hi>Straffords</hi> innocence: and Sir <hi>Lewis Dives</hi> having heard of ſuch a Copy in the Houſe of a Citizen of good quality, where he heard me mentioned as a perſon fit to have his name fixt upon poſts, that <hi>I</hi> might be torn in pieces by the people, upon that reaſon earneſtly deſired me to give him a true Copy of what <hi>I</hi> had ſaid in that argument, which I did, &amp; he forthwith gave direction for the printing it, without a privity of mine. Yet, if I had conſented to it, and directed it, <hi>I</hi> profeſſe I ſhould little have imagined, that (at a time when there was ſuch an univerſall licenſe taken to print every thing, of how great irreverence ſoever,) either to Church or State, with impurity, a Speech made in the Houſe of Commons, a Speech ſo narrowly and ſeverly ſifted, and examined there, and yet let paſſe without the leaſt cenſure, either on the Speech it ſelf, or the Author: that the printing of ſuch a Speech ſhould riſe to ſo high a nature, as to make me for ever uncapable of any Honour or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the Commonwealth, I profeſſe could hardly have falne within my reaſon or fears to ſuſpect. And yet three moneths after the fact com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, after the Printing of an hundred Speeches more by other men, after my having ſeverall times ſued, and preſſed for a hearing, whileſt I was of the Houſe of Commons, after by his Majeſties favour <hi>I</hi> had ſate ſix weekes a Member of the Houſe of Peers, after all this, no leſſe a judgement (as far as the Vote of the Houſe of Commons could contribute to it) paſſed upon me unheard, over and above the ſhame of having the Speech it ſelfe burned by the hand of the Hangman. How <hi>I</hi> bore this affliction, with what anxiety of mind to my ſelfe, with what temper and ſubmiſſion to that Honourable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, from whence the blow came, as many of my neer friends can teſtifie the firſt, ſo the envy or malice of no man, can reaſonably and juſtly taxe me as unto the other. How other young men, upon no greater a ſtock of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence then mine, might have ſuffered themſelves to be tranſported up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch misfortunes, (not to give them any other term) <hi>I</hi> leave to thoſe to judge, who have not beene ſo long brought up in the Schoole of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p>As this cenſure fell upon me for many moneths after the fault obiected ſo it reſted in thoſe wals where it begun without ever deſiring a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb facs="tcp:171658:5"/> Court, where <hi>I</hi> was onely to be judged, and where <hi>I</hi> could onely anſwer for my ſelfe, and hope for a vindication: which increaſed my ſufferings to an unſpeakable height, that <hi>I</hi> could by no means cleer my ſelfe in the place where <hi>I</hi> received the wound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor could take notice of it, where <hi>I</hi> might be cleered by my Peers, for feare of breach of priviledge of Parliament: though my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſure were knowne to all the Kingdom, yea, <hi>I</hi> may ſay my infamy in print with forreign Nations.</p>
            <p>Under this weight (enough to have broken a body, and a minde better prepared for theſe exerciſes than mine) <hi>I</hi> ſuffered, till the rudeneſſe and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of that Rabble, drave both their Maieſties, for the ſafety of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their children, to <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, whither by command <hi>I</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them. In this ſhort journey many Souldiers and Commanders (who had aſſembled themſelves, ioyntly to ſolicite the payment of their arrears for the late Northern expedition, from the two Houſes of Parliament) wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on their Maieſties, and leaving them at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, provided their own accommodations at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> the next place of receipt, and ſtill ſo u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the over-plus of company, which the Court it ſelfe could not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. To theſe Gentlemen, of whom few or none were of my acquaintance: and to this place was <hi>I</hi> ſent by His Maieſty, with ſome expreſſions of His Maieſties good acceptance of their ſervice, and returning the ſame night to <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, continued my attendance to <hi>Windſor,</hi> whither their Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties then repaired. <hi>I</hi> had not been there one day, when <hi>I</hi> heard that both Houſes of Parliament were informed, that <hi>I,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Lunsford,</hi> a perſon with whom <hi>I</hi> never exchanged twenty words in my life, had appeared in a warlike manner at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> to the terror of the Kings Liege people: and thereupon had ordered that the Sheriffe of <hi>Surrey,</hi> and as <hi>I</hi> conceive, that all other Sheriffes throughout <hi>England,</hi> ſhould raiſe the power of their ſeverall Counties, to ſuppreſſe the Forces that he and <hi>I</hi> had levyed.</p>
            <p>When firſt this news was brought me, <hi>I</hi> could not but ſlight it, as a redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous rumour: for being moſt certain, that <hi>I</hi> had never been at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> but only upon that meſſage of the Kings, to forty or fifty Gentlemen, totally ſtrangers to me, with whom <hi>I</hi> ſtayed not the ſpace of halfe an houre at moſt, and in no other equipage, than a Coach and ſix hired horſes, with one ſingle man in the Coach with me, and one ſervant riding by: <hi>I</hi> thought it utterly impoſſible for the moſt R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mancy it ſelfe, at ſo neere a diſtance, to raiſe out of that any ſerious matter of ſcandall, or preiudice upon me. But when ſoon after, <hi>I</hi> received from ſome of my friends, not onely a confirmation of that ſeeming impoſſibility, but a particular accompt of the manner of it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſome information concerning me at <hi>Kingſton</hi> had been referred to the examination of a Committee of my ſharpeſt enemies: how the ſix Coach horſes <hi>I</hi> appeared with there, we returned by them into ſix ſcore horſes, and that miſtake, <hi>I</hi> know not by what prevalence of my unhappineſſe, or of my enemies credit, not ſuffered to be rectified by other witneſſes there, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the truth: Finding my ſelfe in this ſad condition, but twenty myles off, and not knowing how the people in other places might be terrified, if reports concerning me ſhould ſpread but in a proportionable rate, to remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtances, they being now derivable from ſuch conſiderable Authors, <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſſe <hi>I</hi> then began to looke upon my ſelfe as a perſon of that rare
<pb facs="tcp:171658:5"/> misfortune, that my reputation would not weigh down the moſt improbable or impoſſible accuſation, but fit to receive any imputation of guilt, the moſt miſchievous or malicious inſtrument of calumny could invent. And in this condition, with no other diſcontent then not beleeving my ſelfe much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to the world for good uſage, <hi>I</hi> procured His Majeſties Licence, to tranſport a perſon of ſo great inconvenience and danger, out of His Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions into another Countrey; and with all poſſible ſpeed removed my ſelfe into <hi>Holland,</hi> never ſuſpecting that my guilt would increaſe with my abſence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the retired private life which <hi>I</hi> had reſolved on, and did according to that reſolution, lead beyond ſea; having the vanity of ſome hope, that a little time diſcovering the falſehood of ſome things beleeved of me, would take away the inconvenience of other things that were but unworthily ſuſpected. Some weeks <hi>I</hi> reſted there without any new hurt, til the falſhood of a perſon, to whoſe truſt <hi>I</hi> comitted a Packet, brought it to a hand well contented with any occaſion to ſatisfie his own particular private malice &amp; revenge upon me; and ſo my Letters, one to the Queens Majeſtie, and the other to my Brother Sir <hi>Lewis Dives,</hi> were publikely brought to be read in both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; from thence new arguments of guilt are ſo far inforced againſt me, and the former diſpleaſure revived and heightned to ſuch a pitch, that at the ſame time I heard of the interception of my Letters, I found my ſelfe accuſed of High Treaſon too, and that for levying war againſt the King; a crime certainly that of all other, I could leaſt ſuſpect my ſelfe guilty of. And to ſay the truth, it came into my charge but by accident; for being in generall charged of high Treaſon, and the impeachment in particular, bearing onely that I had appeared in warlike manner, to the terror of the Kings Subjects, a queſtion was raiſed by a Lord or two, learned in the Law, whether that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation would amount to Treaſon, or no, and ſo leave was deſired to amend the charge, which being granted to make ſure worke, by the Statute of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. it was put in, that I had leavyed War againſt the King. If I were guilty, or ſuſpected of ſo loud a crime, how it came to ſleep ſo long, or if not, how theſe Letters (wherein upon an unpartiall ſurvey, there will not bee found ſo much as an opinion as unto peace or war) could miniſter occaſion for a charge of my levying war againſt the King, I leave to equall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I am far from cenſuring or diſputing the reſolution, or opinion of both, or either Houſe of Parliament; no man receives a ſtroke from thence with more ſubmiſſion and humility, and the great reverence I bear to it, hath made ſuch an impreſſion in me, that the weight of their diſpleaſure hath added many years to me, but in ſo neer a concernment of my life, and my honour, that grave Aſſembly may give me leave, without preſuming to thinke their judgements uniuſt, to ſay, their evidence may be untrue, and the perſons truſted by them, not ſo full of honor, ingenuity, or integrity, ſo free from paſſion, malice, intereſt, or affection, as they are thought. It will be no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, or diſ-reſpect to that great Councell to ſay, that I have many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who have uſed all the ill arts, their wit or malice could ſuggeſt, to bring this affliction upon me, and have not in whiſpers, or in the darke publiſhed their reſolution to deſtroy me; witneſſe the known tampering with very many perſons, both by threats, and promiſes, to accuſe me; their creating and cheriſhing ſuch monſtrous untruths of my treating with the <hi>Danes,</hi> and other
<pb facs="tcp:171658:6"/> forreigne power of a great treaſon of mine plotted, and diſcovered at <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne,</hi> with mighty warlike preparations there: of my being at the head of the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the like; to make me odious to the people, to whoſe rage and violence they have often endeavoured to give me up a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; the deepe ſenſe <hi>I</hi> have of my afflictions and injuries, ſhall never tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me to heighten the repreſentation of them to the leaſt degree beyond truth; but who ever ſhall conſider the penalty of Treaſon, the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation it it brings to families, the brand and infamy it fixes on our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſhall remember that this portion was deſigned to me, for going on my Maſters errant, in a Coach and ſix horſes, will beleeve that a mixture of ſorrow and innocence, with ſo much paſſion as may keepe them company, may well be allowed to breath it ſelfe with ſo much freedome, as to preſent to the world with a true and ſenſible life, my ſufferings, upon whomſoever the injuſtice and inhumanity may light, of having oppreſt and bow'd downe to the earth, a young man and all his hopes, by ſuch undeſerved Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Since that time, other letters of mine or copies of letters (poſſibly never ſent) have had the ſame fortune, and been publiſhed to the world, to ſhew the follies and indiſcretions of a man, enough in her disfavour before, with Gloſſes and Comments to informe the people how much of the dangerous and pernicious Counſells, pretended to be then, and ſtill on foot, had paſſed through my hands, and how great an enemy I am to Parliaments, to this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt grievous and venemous imputation, I hope God will have preſerved me ſome kinde of Antidote in mens memories, of what part I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to bear in the paſſing of the Trieniall Bill, and to it <hi>I</hi> ſhall onely ſay thus much; That I have had the honor to be a Member of the one Houſe, and muſt preſume to thinke my ſelfe ſtill a Member of the other; that I value the honor, the dignity, and the priviledges of both, infinitely above the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and benefits of life, and if I ever wilfully contributed, or ſhall ever conſent to the prejudice of either, I wiſh the deſires of all my enemies may fall upon me.</p>
            <p>To that of my having had ſo great a hand in ill Counſels, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to be of His Majeſties removing from <hi>London,</hi> to a place of ſafety, and the like: I ſhall be bold to ſay, That the Letter to the Queens Maieſty, from whence my enemies would make the inference, hath not with any conſiderer, the leaſt propending of advice any way, but is meerly an accompt of mine own intentions to apply my ſelfe to His Maieſties ſervice, either by abſence, or attendance, according to courſe, that His Maieſty in His wiſedom ſhould think fit to take. Every body knows I never had the honor to be a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, neither have <hi>I</hi> preſumed, without being queſtioned by His Maieſtie, to interpoſe in His Affairs: when He hath graced me with any queſtion, I have anſwered with the freedome of a Subiect, and a Gentleman. But had <hi>I</hi> been a Counſellor, having ſeen what I have ſeen, and heard what <hi>I</hi> heard, <hi>I,</hi> who have known ſuch members of both Houſes, marked out by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for bleſſings, and ſuch for ſacrifice: I who can ſay with truth, that ſuch of that rabble, cryed out, the King's the Traytor: ſuch that the young Prince would governe better: I who can prove that a Leader of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the heate and violence of the tumult, cryed out, That the King was
<pb facs="tcp:171658:6"/> not fit to live. Had I been a Counſellor, what had I beeen (as the learning of Treaſon was then underſtood) ſhould I not have adviſed His Maieſty to withdraw to a place of ſafety, not from His Parliament, but from that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent and unruly multitude, who had already brought into ſo much hazard the perſons and the liberty of this, till then moſt happy Parliament, and not ſtaying there, did ſo loudly threaten ruine, even to the ſacred Perſon of the King; Advertiſe his Maieſty I did of the anger, adviſe him I could not, I had neither the ability, nor the authority.</p>
            <p>In my Letter to the Queene, at her firſt comming into <hi>Holland,</hi> it was obſerved, that in that expreſſion, [of welcoming her from a Countrey not worthy of her] I ſhewed much venome an rancour to my own Nation. I meant it not, and muſt appeale to thoſe who are beſt acquainted with the civility of language, whether the addreſſe might not be comely to any Lady of quality, who ſhould upon any not pleaſing occaſion, leave one Countrey for a while, to reſide in another: And I hope ere long to welcome her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie back from a place not ſo unworthy of her, unto this Nation moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of her, without either diſparagement to <hi>Holland,</hi> or complement to thoſe to whom the unworthy of that Letter was intended.</p>
            <p>For the charge of boldneſſe, and preſumption in ſome expreſſions of thoſe Letters (though I might be glad to compound my treaſon for incivility) ſince the ſuſpicion of that depends upon the right underſtanding of language, and connexion of words: it will be no diſ-reſpect to any, through whoſe hands they have paſſed, to beleeve, that as they were otherwiſe intended by me, ſo that they are capable of other interpretation. However, if in truth, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding, or ill breeding hath produced the other: I hope the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will onely be, that I am an ill Courtier, or an ill Secretary, both which I do humbly confeſſe, not that I am no good Engliſh man, no good Subiect. If in any of thoſe Letters there were any expreſſions of diſcontent or bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, I ſhall ſay little more, than that they paſſed an examination they were not prepared for, and fell into hands that they were not directed to; and I am confident that many honeſt Gentlemen, who have had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to preſerve their papers from ſuch an inquiſition and ſhall conſider the caſe they might be in, if all their ſecret conferences, and private letters were expoſed and produced to the publick view, will caſt up theſe letters of mine, in the number of my misfortunes, without making any addition to my faults; and certainly, whoever ſhall obſerve the meaſure of my ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, with any kinde of indifference, will eaſily forgive ſuch eruptions of paſſion, as were onely vented by me to a brother, though they came within the reach of any other care.</p>
            <p>To draw now to a period of my unfortunate ſtory, which I cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe my ſelfe, from the generality, ſo much charity as to vouchſafe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, further then meere curioſity ſhall lead them; I returned into <hi>England</hi> not with ſo much ioy to ſee my Countrey, as hope to be admitted upon my humble Petition to His Maieſtie, to a faire, regular, impartiall vindication of my innocencie, and proteſted to God, I look upon the time I may naturally hope to live with no other comfort, than as it may make me ſtill capable of that happines. I have infirmities enough about me to make me ask the pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of every wiſe and good man, but for treaſon, or for any voluntary crime (either
<pb facs="tcp:171658:7"/> again my Sovereign or my Country) I ſay it with all humility, I will not accept a Pardon from the King and Parliament. By the grace of God it ſhall never be ſayd, that either the Parliament hath brought me, or His Maieſty expoſed me to a triall, my own uprightneſſe ſhall conſtantly ſolicite it, and without recourſe in this to either of their favours, <hi>I</hi> will either ſtand a iuſtified man to the world, or fall an innocent. But in the mean time, till it pleaſe God to bleſſe this Nation with ſuch a compoſure of the preſent diſtractions, as that Government and Law may have their rightfull and comfortable courſe, <hi>I</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore onely ſo much charity from men, as may ſeem due to one, whoſe good intentions to his Countrey have been in ſome ſort publikly manifeſted, whoſe ill are yet but obſcurely and improbably ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let the few years <hi>I</hi> have liv'd be examined, and if there be found any rancour or venome in my nature, even toward particular perſons, which might in time contract it ſelfe to an enmity againſt the State; if <hi>I</hi> have been a fomenter of iealouſies and debate, or a ſecret conſpirer againſt the honor and fame of any man; if <hi>I</hi> have worne Religion as a maske and vizard for my hypocriſie, and underhand cheriſhed any opinions that <hi>I</hi> have not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed; if <hi>I</hi> been led by any hopes of preferment to flattery, or by the miſſe of it, to revenge; if <hi>I</hi> have been tranſported with private ambition, and been enclined to ſacrifice the leaſt branch of the publike peace and happines, to my own ends and advantage; let the complication of all theſe ills prepare a iudgement of treaſon it ſelfe upon me, and let me be looked upon as a man who hath made a progreſſe in wickedneſſe, that a few years more added to that account, would render me a prodigie to the world. But if in truth my life hath been pleaſant to me under no other Nation, then as I might make it uſefull to my Countrey, and have made it my buſineſſe to beget and continue a good intelligence amongſt good men; if I have beene then moſt zealous and fervent for the liberties of the Subiect, when the power of Court was moſt prevalent, and for the rights of the Crown, when popular licenſe was moſt predominant; if by my continuall ſtudy and practiſe of Religion, <hi>I</hi> have alwayes been a true ſonne of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and by my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and application of my actions to the known rule of the Law, <hi>I</hi> have alwayes been a true ſonne of the State of <hi>England;</hi> if my actions have been honeſt, and my words onely doubtfull, if my life onely clouded with many imperfections, <hi>I</hi> hope the world will beleeve, <hi>I</hi> have been overtaken with too great a meaſure of unhappineſſe, and every generous heart will eaſe me of ſome part of my burthen, by giving the benefit of his good opinion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
